Hey, my name is Maximilian Raff,
and in my dissertation I developed
mathematical tools to analyze and generate
efficient periodic motions
in robotic systems.
When we build legged robots,
we imagine them doing all kinds
of repetitive tasks: moving objects,
performing field operations,
and navigating varied terrain
at different speeds.
So we need a library
of repeatable motion patterns,
or gaits, like walking or running.
And because the robot
runs on a single battery charge,
these gaits must be energy-efficient.
Finding these periodic gaits is challenging
because the motion space
is highly dynamic and nonlinear,
while the actuation space
is constrained by underactuation.
A key idea in my work is
to first study the robot's motions
without actuation, setting the
actuation input to zero
and focusing purely on its natural,
unforced dynamics.
These natural dynamics also appear
in passive dynamic walkers
that move downhill
powered only by gravity.
This leads to the central question:
can natural dynamics
help us design and control
energy-efficient legged systems?
My dissertation contributes in three areas:
systematically generating gait libraries
using continuation methods,
achieving energy efficient motion
through optimal control,
and leveraging natural dynamics
from unactuated passive gaits,
All centered around the idea
that a robot's natural dynamics
shape its energy-optimal gait libraries.
Besides passive robots
that use environmental energy
to compensate losses from joint friction
and foot impacts,
there's also a fully lossless class
of systems that conserve all their energy.
They are theoretical,
but incredibly useful for exploration
because the periodic gaits
can continuously morph
from hopping in place
to walking and running.
Using a general mathematical abstraction
based on hybrid dynamics,
I proved that these periodic orbits
are fundamentally connected.
And with continuation methods
I show how entire gait families
can be systematically generated,
starting from something
as simple as standing still.
But how do these passive gaits
connect to generally actuated gaits?
Well, since they use zero actuation,
they don't draw any energy,
That makes them globally optimal
for a wide class
of energetic cost functions.
Using continuation methods again,
paired with insight from optimization,
I show how it's possible to systematically
generate optimal gait libraries
that originate from the two classes
of passive dynamics,
showcasing how this continuous path
of optimal gaits can be followed
in both simple
and much more complex-legged systems.
This approach reveals
how a system's structure,
like adding elastic springs,
shapes energy use,
and guides the joint optimization
of hardware and control.
Beyond legged robots,
it can extend to exoskeletons
and prostheses,
offering a systematic way
to connect design, control, and efficiency.